Register of the Vladimir Konstantinovich Bukovskiĭ papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vladimir Konstantinovich Bukovskiĭ papers
1928-2011
2017C22
Hoover Institution Archives
52 manuscript boxes, 4 card file boxes, 1 oversize box (24.5 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, notes, reports, Soviet government documents, printed matter, and photographs relating to civil liberties in the Soviet Union, post-Soviet Russia and elsewhere, political conditions in post-Soviet Russia, and promotion of international democracy.
Bukovskiĭ, Vladimir Konstantinovich, 1942-
Access
The collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2017.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at https://searchworks.stanford.edu. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Vladimir Konstantinovich Bukovskiĭ (Bukovsky) document his activities from 1983 to 2004 and include biographical material; correspondence; writings by Bukovskiĭ, among them his conference papers; materials concerning publication of his books with related correspondence; and photographs depicting Bukovskii with other dissidents, political figures, family, and friends.
The correspondence is mostly legal, relating to Bukovskiĭ's legal cases and in defense of other human rights activists (not only Russian/Soviet), and includes letters from Margaret Thatcher, Winston Churchill, Zbigniew Brzezinski, and others, and Bukovskii's letters to Boris Yeltsin.
The International Human Rights Organizations File document Bukovskiĭ's involvement in various human rights organizations concerned with the treatment of dissidents. It includes materials from various organizations, such as Resistance International, National Endowment for Democracy, Center for Democracy, Freedom of Communication, Andrei Sakharov Institute, and Komitet soldatskikh materei (Committee of Soldiers' Mothers). The materials reflect the advocacy in defense and educational work by these groups, including statements and letters supporting dissident movements.
In 1992, after the dissolution of the Soviet Union, President Yeltsin's government invited Bukovskiĭ to serve as an expert witness at the trial of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (CPSU) before the Constitutional Court. Russia's communists were suing Yeltsin for banning their Party and confiscating its property. To prepare his testimony, Bukovskiĭ was granted access to the documents from the CPSU Central Committee archives. He managed to scan many documents (some with high security clearance) secretly, including KGB reports to the Central Committee. The copies were then smuggled to the West and now they are available online at http://www.bukovsky-archives.net/. A number of documents were extensively quoted and cited in Bukovskiĭ's Judgment in Moscow. The collection also includes copies of these archival materials.
Biographical Note
1942 Born, Belebey, Bashkir ASSR, Soviet Union.
1960 Entered Moscow University to study biology.
1961 Wrote his critical notes on the Communist Youth League (Komsomol) and was expelled from the university.
1963-1965 Arrested, charged with "anti-Soviet agitation and propaganda," and sent for treatment at the Special Psychiatric Hospital in Leningrad.
1965 Helped to organize a demonstration on Pushkin Square in central Moscow to protest against the trial of the writers Andrei Sinyavsky and Yuli Daniel (Glasnost rally).
1965-1966 Arrested, charged with organizing the demonstration, and kept in various psychiatric hospitals.
1967-1970 Advocated for the right to organize demonstrations and other public protests, arrested, and sentenced to three years in an "ordinary regime" corrective-labor camp.
1971 Managed to smuggle to the West over 150 pages documenting abuse of political prisoners in psychiatric institutions in the Soviet Union.
1972 Accused of slandering Soviet psychiatry, contacts with foreign journalists, and the possession and distribution of Samizdat. Sentenced to two years in prison, five in a labor camp, and five more in internal exile.
1976 Deported from the USSR and exchanged by the Soviet government for the imprisoned general secretary of the Communist Party of Chile, Luis Corvalán, at Zürich airport. Settled in Great Britain, Cambridge.
1978 Gained a master's degree in Biology at Cambridge University.
1978 Author, To Build a Castle: My Life as a Dissenter.
1983 Co-founded Resistance International, along with Cuban dissident Armando Valladaresand, and was later elected a president of the organization.
1985 Resistance International expanded into the American Foundation for Resistance International.
1987 Author, To Choose Freedom
1991 Visited Moscow for the first time since his deportation fifteen years prior. His Soviet-era convictions were annulled by a decree of the RSFSR Supreme Court and his Russian citizenship was restored.
1992 Nominated aa a candidate for elections of Mayor of Moscow.
1996 Author, Judgment in Moscow: Soviet Crimes and Western Hypocrisy
1998 Director of the Gratitude Fund.
2001 Elected President of the Comitatus pro Libertatibus – Comitati per le Libertà – Freedom Committees in Florence. Received the Truman-Reagan Medal of Freedom.
2004 Co-founded the Committee 2008 for free and fair presidential elections in 2008, with Garry Kasparov, Boris Nemtsov, Vladimir V. Kara-Murza, and others.
2006 Accused Vladimir Putin of the assassination of Aleksander Litvinenko.
2007 Officially nominated to run for president in the 2008 Russian presidential election.
2009 Joined the council of the new Solidarnost' coalition.
2014 Author, Putin's Secret Empire: Will There Be a "Palace Coup"?
2015 Accused Vladimir Putin of the assassination Boris Nemtsov.
2018 Member of the international advisory council for the Victims of Communism Memorial Foundation Director of the Gratitude Fund Member of the International Council of the Human Rights Foundation Senior Fellow at the Cato Institute in Washington, D.C.
Civil rights--Soviet Union.; Civil rights.; Democracy.; Dissenters--Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation)--Politics and government--1991-
- Biographical File, 1976-2011
  Scope and Contents note
  Awards, curriculum vitae, financial documents, naturalization records, and publicity file, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Awards and honorary degrees, 1981-2011
    General note
    See also: Oversize Material, box 57.
    - "Human Rights Award," American Federation of Teachers, AFL-CIO, 1981 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - "Krieble Freedom and Democracy Award," Krieble Institute, circa 1990 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - "Magyar Köztársasági Érdemrend Középkeresztje," Magyarország köztársasági elnöke, certificate, 2011 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - "Pro Libertate Hungariae," World Federation of the Hungarian Freedom Fighters, certificate, 1981 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Curriculum vitae, circa 1990 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Financial documents, 1978-1988 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    Includes correspondence, statements, and reports.
  - Naturalization papers, 1988-1991 (Box-folder 1: 7-8)
    Includes a guide for applicants, correspondence, and "Certificate of Naturalization as a British Citizen."
  - Publicity file, 1976-1997
    Worldwide press clippings in chronological order.
    - 1976-1979 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - 1982-1983 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - 1990-1993 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - 1996-1997 (Box-folder 1: 15)
- Correspondence, 1976-2000
  Letters, postcards, invitations, and enclosures, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - General, 1976-1995 (Box-folder 1: 16-17)
  - Invitation letters, postcards, and notes, 1980-1993 (Box-folder 1: 18, Box-folder 54: 3)
  - Unidentified, 1983-1996 (Box-folder 1: 19, Box-folder 54: 2)
    Includes photographs.
  - Aban'kin, Vitol'd, 1990-1997 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Akifman, Galina, 1995 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Alekseeva, Liudmila, 1977-1983 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Alloi, Vladimir, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Almond, Mark, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Anastasi, Paul, 1988 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Arkhangelskii, Maksim, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Association for Free Russia, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Bakhmin, Viacheslav, 1993 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    Includes materials relating to the human rights activist Petro Grigorenko.
  - Banfi, Alessandro, 1985 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Baranov, Leonid, 1997 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Bax, Joss, 1993 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Bernstein, Lev B., 1992 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Besançon, Alain, 1995 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Betchell, Nicolas, 1991 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Boll (Böll), Heinrich Theodor, 1984 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Borovoi, Konstantin, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Bovy, J. M., 1986 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Brzezinski, Zbigniew Kazimierz (Center for Strategic & International Studies, Washington, D.C.), 1988-1989 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Bukovskaia, Nina Ivanovna, 1976-1985 (Box-folder 2: 20)
    Includes material regarding Iurii Titov.
  - Bukovskaia, Ol'ga, undated (Box-folder 54: 6)
  - Burbulis, Gennadii, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Cadorgan, Peter, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 2: 22-23)
    Includes printed matter.
  - Carter-Ruck, Peter F., 1986 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Cate, Curtis, 1986 (Box-folder 2: 25)
    Includes materials relating to the Veritas Softcover Book Series project.
  - Cathie, Paul, 1982 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Chambers, Norman C., 1993 (Box-folder 2: 27)
    Includes materials relating to Bukovskiĭ's consulting service to Brown & Root, Inc. concerning the Rosshelf Company.
  - Cheng-kung, Ku, 1983 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Chitester, Robert J., 1992 (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - Chirac, Jacques, President of France, 1995 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - Chukanov, Vadim, 1992 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Churchill, Winston Spencer (House of Commons), 1982-2000 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Chwiakowska, Luiza, 1998 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Comité Martchenko, 1983 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Corner, Richard, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Danielson, Elena, 1998 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Davidenko, V., circa 1991 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Decter, Midge, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Delaunay, Michel, 1994 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Diomedes Inc., 1990 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Djilas, Aleksa, 1984 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Dolan, Anthony, 1983 (Box-folder 3: 12)
    Includes "Remarks of the President to the Conservative Political Action Conference Dinner."
  - Dorokhin, German G., 1993 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Duborenko, Vera, 1982 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Dukstra, J., 1995 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Efimov, Boris, circa 1980 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Ericson, Edward E., 1993 (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - Ermakov, Georgii, 1991 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - The European Foundation, 1996 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Filanovskii, Igor' and Tatiana, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - Fiskesjö, Magnus, 1984 (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - Ford, Charles, 1984 (Box-folder 3: 22)
  - Frankel, Mark S., 1992 (Box-folder 3: 23)
  - Freeman, Connie, 1984 (Box-folder 3: 24)
  - Frick, H. W., 1983 (Box-folder 3: 25)
  - Geimer, William W., 1993 (Box-folder 3: 26)
  - Gerashchenko, Igor, 1992 (Box-folder 3: 27)
  - Getman, Igor, 1992 (Box-folder 3: 28)
  - Glapinska, Kasia, 1993 (Box-folder 3: 29)
  - Glazov, Iurii, 1983 (Box-folder 3: 30)
  - Goldsmith, James, 1993 (Box-folder 3: 31)
  - Graham, Turner, 1983 (Box-folder 3: 32)
  - Grigorenko, Petro, 1977 (Box-folder 3: 33)
  - Grigor'iants, Sergei, 1993 (Box-folder 3: 34)
  - Grivnina, Irina, 1983-1990 (Box-folder 3: 35)
  - Guthrie, John, 1993 (Box-folder 3: 36)
  - Hartman, F., 1984 (Box-folder 3: 37)
  - Heffer, Diana, 1992 (Box-folder 3: 38)
  - Henderson, Michael, 1982 (Box-folder 3: 39)
  - Hodgson, Peter, 1994 (Box-folder 3: 40)
  - Hoskyns, John, 1989 (Box-folder 3: 41)
  - Ilzen, G., 1991 (Box-folder 3: 42)
  - Imber, Sofia, 1982 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Institut Européen Pour La Paix, 1985 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Internationale Gesellschaft für Menschenrechte (IGFM), 1985 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Ivashkin, Andrei, 1996 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Jatras, Jim, 1984-1991 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Jolis, Jack, 1985 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Kaplan, Roger, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Kashirin, A. P., 1996 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Katagoshchin, Vsevolod V., circa 1985 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Kholodkovskii, N., 1986 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Killigrew, Michael, 1985 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Kim, Marat, 1994 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Klimov, Aleksei, 1985 (Box-folder 4: 42)
  - Kozlov, Ruslan V., circa 1990 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Kuzin, Viktor, 2001 (Box-folder 54: 5)
  - Kuzio, Taras, 1991 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Kuznetsov, Eduard, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Kwitny, Jonathan, 1984 (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Ledeen, Michael, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - Lehmann, Mary, 1989-1994 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Lenczowski, John, 1992 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Lerner, Arthur, 1984 (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - Liberty Fund Inc., 1990 (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - Lips, David A., 1989-1990 (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - Liubarskii, Kronid, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - Lozansky, Edward Limonovich, 1993 (Box-folder 4: 24)
    Includes Bukovskiĭ bibliography.
  - Makarov, V., 1998 (Box-folder 4: 25)
    Includes clippings.
  - Margarita, Princess of Romania, 1991 (Box-folder 4: 26)
    Includes "Speech of His Majesty King Michael of Romania at the French Institute for International Affairs," Paris.
  - Markham, David, 1982 (Box-folder 4: 27)
  - Masagaki, Shin-ichi, 1998 (Box-folder 54: 4)
  - Mavros, George J., 1986-1987 (Box-folder 4: 28)
  - McClaughry, John, 1984 (Box-folder 4: 29)
  - McDowall, Christopher, 1992 (Box-folder 4: 30)
  - Mianowicz, Tomasz, 1998 (Box-folder 4: 31)
  - Mihajlov, Mihajlo, 1984 (Box-folder 4: 32)
  - Modor, Adam, 1991 (Box-folder 4: 33)
  - Moksiakov, Vasilii M., 1994 (Box-folder 4: 34)
  - Montaner, Gina, 1985 (Box-folder 4: 35)
  - Moravetskii, Kornel, 1992 (Box-folder 4: 36)
  - Mouravnik, Aleksei, 1984 (Box-folder 4: 37)
  - Murphy, Kenneth, 1992 (Box-folder 4: 38)
  - Nadezhina, Maria, 1991 (Box-folder 4: 39)
  - Nissen, A., 1984 (Box-folder 4: 40)
  - Norquist, Grover, 1992 (Box-folder 4: 41)
  - Nosov, Viktor, 1983-1996 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Odintsov, Igor, 1994 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Osadchenko, Tamara, 1992 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Ozerov, Mikhail, 1992 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Palmer, Robie M. H. (Mark), 1982 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    Includes "Some Recommendations for the Program to Promote Democracy in the Communist Countries," by Bukovskiĭ, typescript.
  - Pavlenkova, Svetlana Borisovna, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Pechorin, Valentin, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Persson, Bo, 1992 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Pestov, Viktor G., 1991 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Petrenko, Maria, 1996 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Polikovskaia, Liudmila V., circa 1980 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Polishchuk, Arkadii, circa 1982 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Poltoranin, Mikhail, 1991 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Reddaway, Peter, 1994 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Rangel, Sofia Imber de, 1983 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - Reilly, Robert, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - Revel, Jean-François, 1989-1998 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - Riegle, Donald W., 1977 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - Risk, Robert G., 1983 (Box-folder 5: 19)
  - Roberts, J., 1992 (Box-folder 5: 20)
  - Rogachii (Rogatshi), Inna, 1992-1995 (Box-folder 5: 21-22)
    Includes clippings and printed matter.
  - Rotaru, I. V., 1986 (Box-folder 5: 23)
  - Rozek, Edward J., 1992-1994 (Box-folder 5: 24)
  - Rubtsov, Viktor, 2000 (Box-folder 5: 25)
  - Rukshitskaia, Maria, circa 1990 (Box-folder 5: 26)
  - Salvia, 1984 (Box-folder 5: 27)
  - Sandperl, Molly, 1983 (Box-folder 5: 28)
  - Sariban, Alla, 1983 (Box-folder 5: 29)
  - Shananashvili, Marina M., 1993 (Box-folder 5: 30)
  - Shirokii, V. F., 1997 (Box-folder 5: 31)
  - Shishkova, Nadezhda, 1992 (Box-folder 5: 32)
  - Sidorkin, Aleksandr S., circa 1990 (Box-folder 5: 33)
  - Singer, Max, 1984 (Box-folder 5: 34)
  - Singlaub, John K., 1984 (Box-folder 5: 35)
  - Slonim, Iris, circa 1990 (Box-folder 5: 36)
  - Smirnov, Aleksei, 1994 (Box-folder 5: 37)
  - Sobchak, Anatolii, 1992 (Box-folder 5: 38)
  - Sobin, A., 1991 (Box-folder 5: 39)
  - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr Isaevich, 1977 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Solzhenitsyna, Natal'ia Dmitrievna, circa 1992 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Somersalo, A. V., 1992 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Soros, George, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    Includes "Report from Central America" by Soros.
  - Springer, Axel, 1979 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Stansfield, Elena, 1985 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Stroilov, Pavel V., 1996 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Swartz, Richard, 1992 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Tarsis-Dormann, Hanni, 1992 (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Tether, Phillip, 1984 (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - Thompson, Elizabeth, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - Tomkiewicz, David, 1983 (Box-folder 6: 13)
  - Torris, Rodolfo Pereira, 1985 (Box-folder 6: 14)
  - Suvorov, Viktor, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Tsymbal, Evgenii, 1992 (Box-folder 6: 15)
  - Tully, M. J., 1984 (Box-folder 6: 16)
  - Ubozhko, Lev, 1991 (Box-folder 6: 17)
  - Ulmanis, Ernests, 1996-2000 (Box-folder 6: 18)
  - Vershin, A., 1992 (Box-folder 54: 1)
  - Vibert, R., O.B.E., Senator, 1983 (Box-folder 6: 19)
  - Vinogradov, Igor', 1993 (Box-folder 6: 20)
  - Voren, Robert van, 1983-1992 (Box-folder 6: 21)
    Includes open letter to Andrei Vorob'ev, Russian Federation Minister of Health, regarding conditions of Russian psychiatric science and "Geneva Initiative on Psychiatry" in Ukraine and Romania.
  - Weinberger, Freiedrich, 1998 (Box-folder 6: 22)
  - Weisblatt, Karen, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 6: 23)
  - Wierzbicki, Piotr, 1997 (Box-folder 6: 24)
  - Yankelevich, Efrem, 1984 (Box-folder 6: 25)
  - Zotova, Venera, 1992 (Box-folder 6: 26)
- Photographs, 1950-2002
  - Featuring Bukovskiĭ, 1957-2003
    - Caricatures of Bukovskiĭ, undated (Box-folder 53: 69)
    - Negatives and slides, undated (Box-folder 54: 27)
    - 1957-1962 (Box-folder 51: 1, Box-folder 54: 19)
    - Late 1970s (Box-folder 51: 2-3)
      Includes a photograph with Viktor Nekrasov.
    - Zurich, 1976 December (Box-folder 51: 4-7)
    - With Gertrudis Hartman, Amsterdam, 1976 December (Box-folder 54: 20)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 51: 8-10, Box-folder 54: 22)
    - With Theodor Bikel, 1977 (Box-folder 54: 24)
    - With Henry M. Jackson, 1977 February (Box-folder 54: 21)
    - With Gertrudis Hartman, Amsterdam, 1977 February (Box-folder 51: 11)
    - Canada, 1977 February-March (Box-folder 51: 12)
    - University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, 1977 November (Box-folder 51: 13)
    - Berlin, 1977 November (Box-folder 51: 14)
    - With George Meany and Lane Kirkland at the American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) convention, Los Angeles, 1977 December (Box-folder 54: 23)
    - London, 1977 Winter (Box-folder 51: 15)
    - With Viktor Nekrasov, Cornelia Gerstenmaier, and others, 1978 October (Box-folder 54: 25)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 54: 26, Box-folder 51: 16-25)
    - Photos by Wilkinson, 1979 January (Box-folder 55: 1)
    - 1979 March (Box-folder 55: 2)
    - 1980 (Box-folder 55: 3, Box-folder 51: 26-35, Box-folder 52: 2-9)
    - Photos by Ilkka Jääaro, 1980 (Box-folder 55: 5)
    - 1980 March (Box-folder 51: 36)
    - With Leopold Unger, Brussels, photo by J. Vandenhoeck, 1980 March (Box-folder 55: 4)
    - Photo by Okky S. Offerhaus, 1980 April (Box-folder 51: 37)
    - With Iurii Yarim-Agaev and others, 1980 November (Box-folder 52: 1)
    - Cambridge, 1980 (Box-folder 52: 10-11)
    - Photo by Peter Mitchell, 1980 (Box-folder 51: 38)
    - Committee for the Defense of the Unjustly Prosecuted, 1980 (Box-folder 51: 39)
    - With Leonid Pliushch, 1980 (Box-folder 52: 13)
    - With Mikhail Shemiakin, 1980 (Box-folder 52: 12)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 51: 40, Box-folder 55: 6)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 55: 7)
    - Bonn, photos by Teutopress, 1983 August (Box-folder 55: 8)
    - With Helmut Josef Michael Kohl and Karl Walter Claus Carstens, Bonn, photo by Teutopress, 1983 August (Box-folder 55: 9)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 51: 41)
    - With Robert Conquest, John Dunlop, and others, Palo Alto, 1984 (Box-folder 51: 43)
    - With Iurii Yarim-Agaev and Edward Lozansky, San Francisco, 1984 (Box-folder 51: 44)
    - With Gertrudis Hartman, 1984 September (Box-folder 51: 42)
    - With Mstislav Rostropovich at the Resistance International Congress, 1984 or 1985 (Box-folder 51: 72)
    - With Edward Lozansky, Washington, D.C., 1984 or 1985 (Box-folder 51: 73)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 51: 45)
    - Baltic Peace and Freedom Cruise, 1985 (Box-folder 51: 46-47)
    - With Edward Lozansky, 1985 (Box-folder 51: 48)
    - With Iurii Yarim-Agaev and others, 1985 May (Box-folder 51: 49, Box-folder 55: 10)
    - With Robert Conquest, Iurii Yarim-Agaev, and others, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 51: 50)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 51: 51)
    - With Edward Lozansky, 1986 (Box-folder 51: 52)
    - With Leon Nikolin at Raoul Wallenberg exhibition in Vienna, 1986 (Box-folder 51: 53)
    - Photos by Mikhail Lemkhin, 1986 (Box-folder 51: 54-57, Box-folder 55: 11)
    - With Naum Korzhavin, photos by Mikhail Lemkhin, 1986 (Box-folder 51: 58)
    - With Cornelia Gerstenmaier, Milovan Djilas, and Vladimir Voinovich at the Resistance International Congress, 1986 (Box-folder 51: 59)
    - At University of Alberta, 1986 March (Box-folder 51: 60)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 51: 61)
    - California, 1987 (Box-folder 51: 62)
      Includes birthday cards.
    - Fifth Sakharov Congress in Amsterdam, 1987 (Box-folder 51: 63)
    - "Frankfurter Forum,", 1987 (Box-folder 51: 64)
    - 1987-1988 (Box-folder 51: 65)
    - 1988 May (Box-folder 51: 66)
    - With Edward Lozansky, Washington, D.C., 1988 June (Box-folder 51: 67)
    - 1989 (Box-folder 51: 68-71)
    - 1990s (Box-folder 55: 12-13)
    - Capri, album pages, 1980s (Box-folder 50: 6-10)
    - 1990 (Box-folder 52: 14-16)
    - 1990 November (Box-folder 52: 17)
    - With Edward Lozansky and Leonid Pliushch, 1990 November (Box-folder 52: 18)
    - 1991 (Box-folder 55: 14)
    - Moscow, 1991 (Box-folder 54: 15, Box-folder 52: 19-20)
    - Ukraine, 1991 (Box-folder 55: 16, Box-folder 52: 21-24)
    - With Vladimir Gershuni, photos by I. Maev, 1991 (Box-folder 55: 15)
    - With Galina Starovoitova, 1992 (Box-folder 52: 29)
    - Moscow, 1992 (Box-folder 52: 25-26)
    - With Edward Lozansky, 1992 February (Box-folder 52: 27)
    - Boulder, Colorado, 1992 July (Box-folder 52: 28)
    - Colorado, 1993 (Box-folder 52: 30)
    - Luxembourg, photos by Photo-Cine-Studio, 1993 (Box-folder 55: 21)
    - Switzerland, album pages, 1994 (Box-folder 50: 5)
    - 1995 (Box-folder 52: 34)
    - With Edward Lozansky and others, 1995 (Box-folder 52: 33)
    - Embassy of the Russian Federation, 1995 January (Box-folder 52: 31)
      Includes dinner menu signed by participants.
    - With sister Olga (?), 1995 February-March (Box-folder 52: 32)
    - Cambridge, 1996 February (Box-folder 52: 35)
    - With Gertrudis Hartman, 1996 February (Box-folder 52: 36)
    - 1996 April (Box-folder 55: 17)
    - 1996 October (Box-folder 55: 18)
    - 1997 (Box-folder 52: 37)
    - 1997 March-April (Box-folder 52: 38)
    - 1997 June (Box-folder 52: 39)
    - Colorado, 1997 June (Box-folder 52: 40)
    - With Gertrudis Hartman, 1997 June (Box-folder 52: 41)
    - 1997 December (Box-folder 55: 19)
    - Poland, 1998 March (Box-folder 52: 42-48)
    - 1998 May (Box-folder 52: 49)
    - With Ernst Neizvestnyi, 1999 (Box-folder 55: 20)
    - 1999 January (Box-folder 52: 61-62)
    - 1999 May (Box-folder 52: 63)
    - 1990s (Box-folder 52: 50-60)
    - 2000 (Box-folder 52: 64-65)